Guide to the Margaret S. Mahler Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Presentation Files, 1930-1984; Series II; 14 linear feet (35 boxes)
  - "On the Significance of the Rapprochment Sub-phase of the Separation-Individuation Process" Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Institute [Paper], 1972 May 12 (Box 48, Folder 928)
  - "The World of Mother and the World Outside: Some Patterns of Transition" by A. Bergman Margaret S. Mahler Symposium Series Medical College of Pennsylvania and the Eastern Pennsylvania Psychiatric Institute [Discussion], 1972 May 13 (Box 48, Folder 929-931)
  - Early Ego Development and the Dejá Vú by B. L. Pacella New York Psychoanalytic Society [Discussion], 1972 May 30 (Box 48, Folder 932)
  - Notices Hampstead Child-Therapy Clinic, 1972 July 21-23 (Box 48, Folder 933)
  - "Separation-Individuation in the Course of the Life Cycle"-Panel American Psychoanalytic Association [Discussion], 1972 December 3 (Box 49, Folder 934)
  - Untitled, by Dr. Edelheit New York Psychoanalytic Society [Discussion], 1973 March 13 (Box 49, Folder 935)
  - "Early Mothering: Its Relation to Later Ego and Sexual Disturbances" Margaret S. Mahler Symposium Series Medical College of Pennsylvania and the Eastern Pennsylvania Psychiatric Institute [Discussion], 1973 May 19 (Box 49, Folder 936)
  - "The Current Status of Infantile Neurosis"- Panel Association for Child Psychoanalysis [Discussion], 1973 July 22 (Box 49, Folder 937-938)
  - Untitled American Academy of Child Psychiatry [Program], 1973 October 17-21 (Box 49, Folder 939)
  - "Symbiosis and Individuation: The Psychological Birth of the Human Infant" Fifteenth Sophia Mirviss Memorial Lecture San Francisco Psychoanalytic Institute and Mount Zion Hospital and Medical Center [Lecture], 1973 November 5 (Box 49, Folder 940-945)
  - "Vicissitudes of Infantile Omnipotence" Association of Child Psychoanalysis [Paper], 1974 March 24 (Box 50, Folder 946-948)
  - "Emotional Object Constancy" Center for Advanced Psychological Studies [Discussion], 1974 March 29-31 (Box 50, Folder 949)
  - "Symbiosis and Individuation: The Psychological Birth of the Human Infant" Albert Einstein College of Medicine [Lecture], 1974 April 19 (Box 50, Folder 950)
  - Discussion Number Four-Child Case American Psychoanalytical Association [Preparatory Material], 1974 May 1 (Box 50, Folder 951)
  - "Effects of the Loss of Parents on Later Development"-Panel Margaret S. Mahler Symposium Series (5th) Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Institute and Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Society [Discussion], 1974 May 18 (Box 50, Folder 952-953)
  - Pioneers Panel International Association for Child Psychiatry and Allied Professions [Paper], 1974 August 1 (Box 50, Folder 954)
  - Conference on Psychoanalytic Education and Research American Psychoanalytic Association [Report], 1974 September 29-October 4 (Box 50, Folder 955)
  - "Child Psychosis: A Theoretical Statement and its Implications" by M. Furer, M.D., M. Mahler, M.D., and A. Bergman Fourteenth International Congress of Pediatrics [Paper], 1974 October 3-9 (Box 50, Folder 956)
  - "Clinical and Diagnostic Considerations in the Analysis of a Five Year Old Hysteric" by H. Rosner New York Psychoanalytic Institute [Discussion], 1974 October 29 (Box 50, Folder 957)
  - "A Study of the Separation-Individuation Process Application to Borderline Phenomena" New York Psychoanalytic Institute [Paper], 1974 October 30 (Box 50, Folder 958)
  - Developmental Aspects of Transference-Discussion Group 13 American Psychoanalytic Association [Program Material], 1974 December 12 (Box 51, Folder 959)
  - "Some Suggested Revisions Concerning Early Female Development" Discussion by E. Galenson, M.D. and H. Roiphe, M.D. [Discussion], 1975 February 11 (Box 51, Folder 960-961)
  - "Notes on Observations of Early Female Development" Roosevelt Hospital, Grand Rounds [Lecture], 1975 March 19 (Box 51, Folder 962)
  - "The Mirror Dream" by C. Feigelson, M.D. New York Psychoanalytic Institute [Discussion], 1975 March 25 (Box 51, Folder 963)
  - "Die Bedetung des Losloesungs and Individuation Prozesses Fuer die Beurteilung von Borderline-Phenomenon" Deutsche Psychoanalytische Vereinigung [Paper], 1975 April 12 (Box 51, Folder 964)
  - "Symbiosis and Individuation: Die Physische Geburt des Menschenkindes" Deutsche Psychoanalytische Vereinigung [Paper], 1975 April (Box 51, Folder 965)
  - "The Interrelationship of the Rapprochment Subphase and the Infantile Neurosis" Margaret S. Mahler Symposium Series (6th) Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Institute and Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Society [Discussion], 1975 May 17 (Box 51, Folder 966)
  - Untitled Columbia Analytic Course [Lecture], 1975 June 2 (Box 51, Folder 967)
  - "Longitudinal Study of the Treatment of a Psychotic Child-with the 'Tripartite Design': Illustrated with Film" Chestnut Hill Lodge Symposium [Paper], 1975 October 3 (Box 51, Folder 968)
  - "Separation-Individuation Process: Adaptation and Defense InStatu Nascendi: with Film Illustration" Eastern Pennsylvania Psychiatric Institute [Paper], 1975 (Box 52, Folder 969)
  - U. S. A. Award United Jewish Appeal, Federation of Jewish Philanthropies Joint Campaign [Lecture], 1976 January 18 (Box 52, Folder 970)
  - Untitled American Psychoanalytic Association [Film Text, Promotional Material], 1976 May 5-10 (Box 52, Folder 971)
  - "Developmental Aspects in the Assessment of Narcissistic and So-called Borderline Personalities" by M. Mahler, M.D. and L. Kaplan, Ph.D. International Conference on Borderline Disorders; Topeka, Kansas [Paper], 1976 March 18-21 (Box 52, Folder 972-979)
  - "Developmental Aspects in the Assesment of Narcissistic and So-called Borderline Personalities" by M. Mahler, M.D., and L. Kaplan, Ph.D. International Conference on Borderline Disorders; Topeka, Kansas [Paper], 1976 March 18-21 (Box 53, Folder 980-984)
  - Workshop in Honor of Margaret S. Mahler Institute for the Study of Psychotherapy [Commemorative addresses], 1977 March 6 (Box 53, Folder 985)
  - Special Tribute to Margaret S. Mahler Roosevelt Hospital, Grand Rounds [Paper], 1977 April 21 (Box 53, Folder 986)
  - Meeting Honoring Margaret S. Mahler New York Society of Freudian Psychologists [Discussion], 1977 April 24 (Box 53, Folder 987)
  - "Meet the Author"-Panel American Psychoanalytic Association [Paper], 1977 April 29 (Box 53, Folder 988)
  - "First Subphase-Normal Separation-Individuation" with Film Illustrations Albert Einstein Medical Center [Lecture], 1977 June 24 (Box 53, Folder 989)
  - "Vicissitudes of the Rapprochment Crisis and the Oedipus Complex" Payne-Whitney Center, New York Hospital-Cornell University [Paper], 1978 April 19 (Box 53, Folder 990-992)
  - "The Rapprochment Crisis and its Solutions" Erik Erickson Institute [Paper], 1978 May 16 (Box 54, Folder 993)
  - "Address to the Annual Meeting of the Margaret S. Mahler Psychiatric Research Foundation" Margaret S. Mahler Psychiatric Research Foundation [Paper], 1978 May (Box 54, Folder 994)
  - "Therapeutic Communication Groups for Preschool Deaf Children: An Application of Separation-Individuation Theory in an Educational Setting" by A. Bergman Lexington School for the Deaf [Discussion], 1978 June 11 (Box 54, Folder 995-996)
  - "On Separation-Individuation" New York Consultation and Referral Service for Psychotherapy, Inc. [Lecture], 1978 December 1 (Box 54, Folder 997)
  - "Problems of Over-Idealization of the Analyst and Analysis" by P. Greenacre, M.D. New York Psychiatric Institute Colloquy [Discussion], 1979 May 7 (Box 54, Folder 998)
  - "Constructive Use of Aggression in the Service of Separation-Individuation" Margaret S. Mahler Symposium Series (10th) Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Institute and Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Society [Paper], 1979 May 19 (Box 54, Folder 999-1003)
  - "Constructive Use of Aggression in the Service of Separation-Individuation Margaret S. Mahler Symposium Series (10th) Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Institute and Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Society [Paper], 1979 May 19 (Box 55, Folder 1004-1006)
  - "History of Psychoanalytical Research in the United States"-Panel American Psychoanalytic Association [Paper], 1979 December 13 (Box 55, Folder 1007)
  - "Object Relationship in Schizophrenia and Perversion" by R. Bak, M.D. Roosevelt Hospital, Grand Rounds [Discussion], Circa 1970s (Box 55, Folder 1008)
  - "Her Current Overview and Film Presentation of the Mother-Child Interview During the Separation-Individuation Process" Film Introduction First World Congress on Infant Psychiatry [Paper], 1980 April 2 (Box 55, Folder 1009)
  - "Separation-Individuation" with Film Illustrations New Jersey Academy of Psychology [Paper], 1980 May 7 (Box 55, Folder 1010)
  - "Separation-Individuation" with Film Illustration New York International Psychiatric Forum [Paper], 1980 August 30 (Box 55, Folder 1011-1012)
  - "Introduction of Dr. John B. McDevitt" A. A. Brill Memorial Lecture [Paper], 1980 November 25 (Box 55, Folder 1013)
  - "Development of the Sense of Self" Margaret S. Mahler Symposium Series (11th) Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Institute and Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Society [Paper], 1981 May 15 (Box 55, Folder 1014)
  - "The Early Years" and "The First Year"-Video Presentations St. Luke's-Roosevelt Hospital Center [Dicsussion], 1981 November 7 (Box 55, Folder 1015)
  - "Object Inconstancy and Paranoid Conspiracy" by H. Blum, M.D. Psychoanalytic Association of New York [Discussion], 1981 November 16 (Box 55, Folder 1016)
  - "Clinical Discussions of Psychotherapeutic Techniques" New York School for Psychoanalytic Psychotherapy [Lecture], 1980/1981 (Box 55, Folder 1017)
  - Mentor-Protege Series 92nd Street Young Men's and Young Women's Hebrew Association [Discussion], 1982 March 14 (Box 56, Folder 1018)
  - "On Some Phenomena of the Emergence of the Self" Margaret S. Mahler Symposium Series (13th) Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Institute and Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Association [Paper], 1982 May 8 (Box 56, Folder 1019)
  - Untitled Austin Riggs Center, Inc. [Paper], 1982 August (Box 56, Folder 1020)
  - "Attachment in the Framework of the Separation-Individuation Theory" Association for the Advancement of Psychoanalysis, Inc. [Paper], 1983 March 19 (Box 56, Folder 1021)
  - "Indicators of the Emergence of the Sense of the Self" with Film Illustrations Second World Congress of Infant Psychiatry [Paper], 1983 March 30 (Box 56, Folder 1022)
  - "The Psychological Birth of the Human Infant: The Separation- Individuation Process" American Psychoanalytic Association [Paper], 1983 April 29 (Box 56, Folder 1023)
  - William A. Schonfeld Award American Society for Adolescent Psychiatry [Lecture], 1983 June 28 (Box 56, Folder 1024)
  - Graduation Address Postgraduate Center for Mental Health [Lecture], 1983 June 28 (Box 56, Folder 1025)
  - "Address on the Occasion of Dr. Blum's Celebration as Editor of the American Journal of Psychoanalysis" American Psychoanalytic Association [Paper], 1983 December 17 (Box 56, Folder 1026)
  - "Implications of Separation-Individuation for the Care and Education of Very Young Children" Sarah Lawrence College, Early Childhood Center [Discussion], 1984 March 10 (Box 56, Folder 1027)
  - Notes American Psychoanalytic Association [Notes], 1984 May 2-6 (Box 56, Folder 1028)
  - "Comments to the Three Papers of the 1984 Symposium" Margaret S. Mahler Symposium Series (15th) Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Institute and Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Society [Paper], 1984 May 12 (Box 56, Folder 1029)
  - Discussion of Dr. Mead's Address [Discussion], undated (Box 56, Folder 1030)
  - "Discussion of Dr. Sylvester's Paper" [Discussion], undated (Box 56, Folder 1031)
  - "Modified Activity Group Therapy With Mixed Group of Four to Five Year Old Children" Hudson Guild Counseling Service [Paper], undated (Box 56, Folder 1032)
  - Workshop on Symbiosis-Individuation Phase [Presentation], undated (Box 56, Folder 1033)
  - Lecture III New York Psychoanalytic Institute, 1950 (Box 57, Folder 1034)
  - Lecture IV: Id, Ego, Superego New York Psychoanalytic Institute, 1950 (Box 57, Folder 1035)
  - Lectures 1-6 Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Institute, 1951 February 3, March 3, March 17, April 7, April 21 (Box 57, Folder 1036)
  - Lecture New York Psychoanalytic Institute, 1952 (Box 57, Folder 1037)
  - Course # 107 New York Psychoanalytic Institute, 1954-1955 (Box 57, Folder 1038)
  - Course # 12, "On the Latency Period" New York Psychoanalytic Institute, 1956-1957 (Box 57, Folder 1039)
  - Course # 102 New York Psychoanalytic Institute, 1959 (Box 57, Folder 1040)
  - Notes for Courses New York Psychoanalytic Institute, undated (Box 57, Folder 1041)
  - Clinical Conferences in Child Analysis Dr. Perlman Presentation New York Psychoanalytic Institute, 1959-1960 (Box 57, Folder 1042)
  - Clinical Conferences in Child Analysis Dr. Magruder presentation New York Psychoanalytic Institute, 1959-1960 (Box 57, Folder 1043)
  - Child Development Course "Infancy and Early Childhood" New York Psychoanalytic Insititute, 1964 October 29, November 12 (Box 57, Folder 1044)
  - Child Development Course Lecture 1 New York Psychoanalytic Institute, 1965 October 14-1967 October 19 (Box 57, Folder 1045-1048)
  - Child Development Course Lecture 1 New York Psychoanalytic Institute, 1969 October 16-1976 November 4 (Box 58, Folder 1049-1055)
  - Child Development Course Lecture 2 New York Psychoanalytic Institute, 1965 November 18-1968 October 24 (Box 58, Folder 1056-1059)
  - Child Development Course Lecture 2 New York Psychoanalytic Institute, 1969 October 23-1976 November 17 (Box 59, Folder 1060-1064)
  - Child Development Course Lecture 3 New York Psychoanalytic Institute, 1965 December 9-1972 November 22 (Box 59, Folder 1065-1067)
  - Child Development Course Lecture 3 New York Psychoanalytic Institute, 1976 November 18-24 (Box 60, Folder 1068-1069)
  - Child Development Course Notes New York Psychoanalytic Institute, undated (Box 60, Folder 1070)
  - Child Development Course Reading Lists New York Psychoanalytic Institute, 1958-1959, undated (Box 60, Folder 1071)
  - Child Development Course New York Psychoanalytic Institute [Discussion], 1977 (Box 60, Folder 1072)
  - Clinical Conference Series Lecture 1 Roosevelt Hospital, 1973 September 19 (Box 60, Folder 1073)
  - Clinical Conference Series Lecture 2 Roosevelt Hospital, 1973 September 25 (Box 60, Folder 1074)
  - Clinical Conference Series Lecture 3 Roosevelt Hospital, 1973 October 10 (Box 60, Folder 1075)
  - Child Analytic Course Columbia University [Lecture], 1975 June 2 (Box 60, Folder 1076)
  - Infant Study Group of the Psychoanalytic Research and Development Fund [Minutes], 1969 (Box 60, Folder 1077-1079)
  - Infant Study Group of the Psychoanalytic Research and Development Fund [Minutes], 1969-1973 (Box 61, Folder 1080-1086)
  - Infant Study Group of the Psychoanalytic Research and Development Fund [Minutes], 1973-1975 (Box 62, Folder 1087-1093)
  - Infant Study Group of the Psychoanalytic Research and Development Fund [Minutes], 1976 (Box 63, Folder 1094)
  - Infant Study Group of the Psychoanalytic Research and Development Fund, 1971-1974, undated (Box 63, Folder 1095-1097)
- Writings, 1924-1984; Series III; 16 linear feet (36 boxes)
  This series is arranged into eight subseries: Articles, Reviews, Scientific Papers: Published; Articles, Reviews, Scientific Papers: Unpublished; Books, Manuscripts: Published; Books, Manuscripts: Unpublished; Books: Volumes; Works-In-Progress; Bibliographies; and Oral Histories and Memoirs. The material is arranged chronologically within the subseries.
  - Articles, Reviews, Scientific Papers: Published
    - Blutbefunde beim Kindlichen Myxödem, Zeitschrift für Kinderheilkunde, 38:688-693., 1924 (Box 64, Folder 1098)
    - (Nobel, E. & Schoenberger M.) "Beitrag zür Prognose der Skrofulose" Zeitschrift für Kinderheilkunde 38:668-676., 1924 (Box 64, Folder 1099)
    - Die Grösse der Gaumentonsillen im Kindesalter, Zeitschrift für Kinderheilkunde 39:367-371., 1925 (Box 64, Folder 1100)
    - (Nobel, E. & Schoenberger M.) "Über die Beeinflussung der Masern durch Rinderserum," Zeitschrift für Kinderheilkunde 39:434-438., 1925 (Box 64, Folder 1101)
    - (Nobel E. & Schoenberger, M.) "Über die Masernprophylaxe each Caronia," Zeitschrift für Kinderheilkunde 40:197-210, 1925 (Box 64, Folder 1102)
    - Zür Kenntnis der thrombpenischen Purpura (Morbis Werlhoffi) im Kindesalter, Zeitschrift für Kinderheilkunde, undated (Box 64, Folder 1103)
    - "Beitrag zur Frage der Dissoziation von Diphtheriertoxin-Antitoxingemischen," Zeitschrift für Kinderheilkunde 41:546-551., 1926 (Box 64, Folder 1104)
    - Über den Vitameingehalt des Knochenmarkes, Zeitschrift für Kinderheilkunde 42:306-309., 1926 (Box 64, Folder 1105)
    - (Kornfeld W. & Schoenberger M.) "Untersuchungen zur Frage der sexuellen Differenzierung einige Körpermasse and Proportionen bei 7 jähringen Kindern," Zeitschrift für Kinderheilkunde 47:676-701, 1929 (Box 64, Folder 1106)
    - (Silberpfennig, I. & Schoenberger, M.) "Der Rorsch'sche Formdeutversuch als Hiffsmittel zum Verständnis der Psychologie Hienkranker," Schweizerarchive für Neurologie undPsychiatrie, 40:302-327., 1938 (Box 64, Folder 1107)
    - Book Review: The Adolescent Personality by Peter Blos. 11:576-578., 1942 (Box 64, Folder 1108)
    - Book Review: The PsychoanalyticalApproach to Juvenile Delinquency by Kate Friedlander, M.D., 1942 (Box 64, Folder 1109)
    - "Pseudoimbecility: A Magic Cap of Invisibility," Psychoanalytic Quarterly, 11:149-164., 1942 (Box 64, Folder 1110)
    - (Rangell, L. & Mahler, M.) "A Psychosomatic Study of Maladie des Tics (Gilles de la Tourette's Disease)," Psychiatric Quarterly, 17:579-603, 1943 (Box 64, Folder 1111)
    - Obituary: "Isador Coriat," Nervous Child, 2:375., 1943 (Box 64, Folder 1112)
    - On the Psychological Problems of Adolescence, New York State Committee on Mental Health Hygiene., 1944 (Box 64, Folder 1113)
    - "Tics and Impulsions in Children: A Study of Motility," Psychoanalytic Quarterly, 13:430-444., 1944 (Box 64, Folder 1114)
    - (Henning, R. & Mahler, M.) Children Must Be Told Too, New York State Committee on Mental Hygiene., 1944 (Box 64, Folder 1115)
    - "Child Analysis," Modern Trends in Child Psychiatry, ed. N.D.C. Lewis and B. Pacella. (NewYork: International Universities Press)., 1945 (Box 64, Folder 1116)
    - "Ego Psychology Applied to Behavior Problems," Modern Trends in Child Psychiatry, ed. N.D.C. Lewis and B. Pacella, (New York: International Universities Press)., 1945 (Box 64, Folder 1117)
    - "Introductory Remarks," Nervous Child, 4:307., 1945 (Box 64, Folder 1118)
    - (Gross, I.H. & Mahler, M.) "Psychotherapeutic Study of A Typical Case with Tic Syndrome," Nervous Child, 4:359-373., 1945 (Box 64, Folder 1119)
    - (Luke, J.; Daltroff, W. & Mahler, M.) "Clinical and Follow-up Study of the Tic Syndrome in Children," American Journal of Orthopsychiatry, 1945 (Box 64, Folder 1120)
    - (Luke, J. & Mahler, M.) "Outcome of the Tic Syndrome," Journal of Nervous Mental Disorders, 103:433-445., 1946 (Box 64, Folder 1121)
    - "Freud's Psychoanalytic Viewpoint for Child Guidance," Handbook of Child Guidance, ed. E. Harms, (New York: Child Care Publications)., 1947 (Box 64, Folder 1122)
    - "Discipline and Punishment," Child Study, 26:69-71, 81-82. 2:1-4., 1949 (Box 64, Folder 1123)
    - "Les Enfant Terribles," Searchlights on Delinquency, Ed. K.R. Essler. (New York: International Universities Press)., 1949 (Box 64, Folder 1124)
    - "Psychoanalytic Evaluation of Tic as a Sign and Symptom in Psychopathology of Childhood," The Psychoanalytic Study of the Child, 3/4:279-310., 1949 (Box 64, Folder 1125)
    - "Remarks on Psychoanalysis with Psychotic Children," Quarterly Journal of Child Behavior, 1:18-21., 1949 (Box 65, Folder 1126)
    - (Ross, J.R., de Fries, Z. & Mahler, M.) "Clinical Studies in Benign and Malignant Cases of Childhood Psychosis (Schizophrenia-like)," American Journal of Orthopsychiatry, 19:295-304., 1949 (Box 65, Folder 1127)
    - "Energy-Economic Considerations in the Learning Process," Quarterly Journal of ChildBehavior, 2:233-236., 1950 (Box 65, Folder 1128)
    - "Helping Children to Accept Death," Child Study, 27:98-99,119-120., 1950 (Box 65, Folder 1129)
    - "Play As A Learning Process," The Exceptional Child, in Infancy and Early Childhood, Proceedings of the 12th Institute of the Child Research Clinic of the Woods School, Langhorne, PA., 1950 (Box 65, Folder 1130)
    - "Professor August Aichorn," Quarterly Journal of Child Behavior, 2:350-351., 1950 (Box 65, Folder 1131)
    - "On Child Psychosis and Schizophrenia: Autistic and Symbiotic Infantile Psychosis," Psychoanalytic Study of the Child, 7:286-305., 1952 (Box 65, Folder 1132)
    - "Residential Treatment of a Schizophrenic Child," Proceedings of Conference at Hawthorne-Cedar Knolls School, 3:53-58., 1952 (Box 65, Folder 1133)
    - (Elkisch, P. & Mahler, M.) "Some Observations on Disturbances of the Ego in a Case of Infantile Psychosis," Psychoanalytic Study of the Child, 8:252-261., 1953 (Box 65, Folder 1134)
    - "Childhood Schizophrenia Roundtable Discussion," American Journal of Orthopsychiatry, 24:523-526., 1954 (Box 65, Folder 1135)
    - "Problems of Infantile Neurosis," Psychoanalytic Study of the Child, 9:56-66., 1954 (Box 65, Folder 1136)
    - "Problems of Technique in Adult Analysis," Seminar by Anna Freud. Bulletin of the PhiladelphiaAssociation for Psychoanalysis, 4:53., 1954 (Box 65, Folder 1137)
    - Discussion of Chapters 13-16. Psychopathology of Childhood, ed. P.H.Hoch & J. Zubin. (New York:Grune & Stratton)., 1955 (Box 65, Folder 1138)
    - (Gosliner, B.J. & Mahler, M.) "On Symbiotic Child Psychosis: Genetic, Dynamic and Restitutive Aspects," Psychoanalytic Study of the Child, 10:195-212., 1955 (Box 65, Folder 1139)
    - (Rabinovitch, R. & Mahler, M.) "The Effect of Marital Conflict on Child Development," Neurotic Interaction in Marriage, ed. V.W. Eisenstein. (New York:Basic Books)., 1956 (Box 65, Folder 1140)
    - Obituary: "Ernst Kris," Journal of theAmerican Orthopsychiatry Association, 1957 (Box 65, Folder 1141)
    - "Autism and Symbiosis, Two Extreme Disturbances of Identity," International Journal of Psycho-Analysis, 39:77-83., 1958 (Box 65, Folder 1142)
    - (Furer, M.; Settlage, C. & Mahler, M.) "Severe Emotional Disturbances in Childhood Psychoses in Children," In: American Handbook of Psychiatry, (New York:Basic Books)., 1959 (Box 65, Folder 1143)
    - (Elkisch, P. & Mahler, M.) "On Infantile Precursors of the 'Influencing Machine' (Tausk)," Psychoanalytic Study of the Child, 14:219-235., 1959 (Box 65, Folder 1144)
    - (Lambert, A.;Moore, V. & Mahler, M.) "A Settlement House Approach to Community Mental Health," Public Health Reports, 74:957- 964., 1959 (Box 65, Folder 1145)
    - Speech of Schizophrenic Children and Their Mothers," American Journal of Orthopsychiatry, discussion. 29:486-490., 1959 (Box 65, Folder 1146")
    - (Furer, M. & Mahler, M.) "Observations on Research Regarding the 'Symbiotic Syndrome' of Infantile Psychosis," Psychoanalytic Quarterly, 29:317-327., 1960 (Box 65, Folder 1147)
    - "Perceptual De-Differentiation and Psychotic 'Object Relationship'," Symposium on Psychotic Object Relations.. International Journal of Psycho-Analysis, 41:548-553., 1960 (Box 65, Folder 1148)
    - "Dé-Différenciation Perceptuelle et [Relation Objectale] Psychotique," Revue Francaise de Psychanalyse, 25:995-1006, 1961 (Box 65, Folder 1149)
    - "Entdifferenzierung der Wahrnehmung and Psychotische "Objektbeziehung," Psyche, suppl. 15:298-305., 1961 (Box 65, Folder 1150)
    - "On Sadness and Grief in Infancy and Childhood: Loss and Restoration of the Symbiotic Love Object," Psychoanalytic Study of the Child, 16:332-351., 1961 (Box 65, Folder 1151)